Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太は➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
数々の困難を何とかくぐり抜け➡
Having overcome multiple obstacles, he's a step closer to a lunar mission.
月ミッションへの新たな一歩を
踏み出そうとしている＞
＜一方 日本人初の
ひびと
ﾑｰﾝｳｫｰｶｰとなった日々人は➡
Meanwhile, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker, but he has an accident and nearly dies.
月面で事故に遭い
死の瀬戸際まで追い詰められる＞
After returning to Earth, he discovers the accident has left him traumatized.
＜地球に帰還したものの➡
事故の影響は心の奥深くに
刻み込まれていた＞
As things stand, since he cannot participate in EVA, he's barred from lunar missions.
＜このままでは船外活動が出来ず
月ミッションには加われない＞
Hibito keeps this information a secret from his
brother, as he heads to chilly Russia to recover.
＜日々人は この事実を
兄･六太にも伏せたまま➡
かつての自分を取り戻すべく
極寒の地 ロシアへと向かった＞
時間切れだよ バトラー室長｡
You're out of time, Chief Butler.
(原田)それで 日々人さんは
どうなるんですか？
So what will happen to Hibito?
ほしか
正直 いい結果とは言えんな｡➡
To be frank, it's not good.
田沼の出したｾｰﾌﾃｨｰｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰの
案が通ってしまった｡➡
Tanuma's "Safety Supervisor" proposal was accepted.
ナサ
もうＮＡＳＡにも
連絡がいってるだろう｡
なんスか それ…｡
They're probably already reaching out to NASA.
What do you mean?
なんば
(南波日々人)はい｡
Yes?
事情を知らぬ者には 日々人君が
昇格したように見えるだろう｡➡
People who don't understand the system will see it as a promotion for him.
But in reality, this position will rob him of any chance to advance.
だが実際 彼はそのﾎﾟｼﾞｼｮﾝを得て
活躍の場を失うことになる｡
言いたくはないが
ほとんど飼い殺し状態だ｡
I hate to say it, but his talents will go to waste.
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#79 Olga, Hibito, and Gagarin
(オリガ)♪～ 僕らの英雄～
Our hero, Mr. Hibbit!
これ いってみっか！
Should I go with this?
いや いきなりこれは➡
No, it's too early for this.
気合入り過ぎだよ コイツって
思われるな｡
He'll think I'm trying too hard...
最初は控えめがいいって
何かの雑誌にも書いてあったしな｡
I remember an article saying you should start by dressing conservatively.
タートルネック！
で コートは大人な黒で｡
A turtleneck!
With a black coat, so I look grown-up.
And to seal the deal...
このブーツ！
These boots!
(オリガ)う～ バヤイ！
Yep, they're crazy!
あと４日かぁ 長いな～｡
Four days to go...
Feels like an eternity...
ああ～！早く 早く これ履いて
ヒビチョフと｡
I can't wait to wear these on a date with Hibichov!
ウフフッ！
あれ？おいイヴァン
訓練始まるぞ｡
Huh?
Hey, Ivan... Training's about to start.
どういう事だ!?ガザエフ！➡
What's going on, Gazzaev?
Why did you approve the transfer without asking me first?
私の確認も取らず
なぜ勝手に承認した!?
Why does Hibichov need to return?!
なぜヒビチョフが
帰らなきゃならんのだ！
まだリハビリ訓練の途中だぞ!?
He's still undergoing rehab.
ハァ～ 日々人には
立派なﾎﾟｼﾞｼｮﾝが与えられたんだ｡
They have a cushy position lined up for Hibito.
あたたかく見送ってやれ
イヴァン｡
Give him a warm send-off, Ivan.
ｾｰﾌﾃｨｰｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰなど➡
Safety Supervisor is a position for retired astronauts...
宇宙飛行士を引退してからでも
できる仕事だろ？
アイツは飛行士として
まだやれる！
That boy still has work to do!
ジャクサ
ＮＡＳＡとＪＡＸＡ
互いに合意の決断だ｡➡
NASA and JAXA made a joint decision...
もはや我々に口出しはできん｡
そうだろう？➡
It isn't for us to interfere. You understand.
他国との関係を保つことが
最優先だ｡➡
We don't want to damage our relationships with other nations.
この程度の話で反発したところで
得することはないだろう｡
There's nothing to be gained by causing trouble over a minor issue.
まだ何とか出来るはずだ！
There must be something we can do.
Ivan, why are you so attached to a Japanese astronaut?
イヴァン
どうして日本人の飛行士に➡
そこまで肩入れするんだ？
おやじ
お前の親父と
同じ病気だからか？
Is it because he suffers from the same disorder as your father?
飛行士のパニック障害など
そう珍しいものではないだろう｡
An astronaut suffering from panic disorder isn't that unusual...
Each decade, it happens to one or two.
１０年に１人 ２人は
必ず出てくる｡➡
Some overcome it, and some don't.
克服できる者もいれば
できない者もいる｡➡
お前の親父がどうだったかは
知らんがな｡
I don't know how your father handled it.
私は父の残した言葉で
揺るぎなく信じているものがある｡
My father once said something that I believe to this day...
Cosmonaut
(Russian Astronaut)
コスモノートは人種にかかわらず
皆 尊敬すべき英雄である｡
All cosmonauts are heroes deserving of respect.
私の父も ヒビチョフもそうだ｡
That includes my father and Hibichov.
イヴァン もう時間だろ
訓練に戻れ｡
Ivan, look at the time.
Return to training.
ヒビチョフ…｡
Hibichov...
I'm heading back tomorrow.
明日には帰れってさ｡
もう少し先に延ばしてくれって
頼んだけど 聞く耳ねぇや｡
I requested some more time, but they weren't having it.
悔しいが どうやら今は
耐える時だ ヒビチョフ｡
I know it's hard, but you have to take what you're given.
下手な反発は危険でしかない｡
Putting up a fight is too risky.
辛抱強く 復帰することだけ
考え続けるんだ｡
So you must endure, and focus on retuning to active duty.
(ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)ねぇ オリガ｡
Hey, Olga...
Hmm?
さっき お父さんから
連絡があってね｡
I just got a call from your father.
ヒビチョフが…｡
Hibichov is...
(イヴァン)ただいま｡
I'm back.
Welcome home.
おかえりなさい｡
オリガは 部屋か？
Is Olga in her room?
ええ 落ち込んでるわ｡
Yes, she was very upset.
⦅中で履いてみたら？⦆
Wanna take a look inside?
⦅うん！⦆
《ｾｰﾌﾃｨｰｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰか…》
Safety Supervisor, huh?
ひま
《暇そうだな》
Sounds boring.
《イヴァンの言う通り➡
Ivan's right.
I'll have to overcome the panic disorder myself.
自分１人でもパニック障害を
克服するしかない》
I can do this.
《出来るはずだ
ヒューストンでも どこでも…》
Whether I'm in Houston or not makes no difference.
はい～｡
Coming.
オリガ…｡
Olga...
Hey...
絶対に帰んなきゃダメなの？
ヒューストンに｡
Do you really have to return to Houston?
ああ 断れるほど偉かないよ｡
Yeah, I don't have any authority over those decisions.
戻ってくる？
So, are you coming back?
わかんないんだ どうなるか｡
I don't know what's going to happen.
ずっとヒューストンかも
しれないし➡
I might be stuck in Houston for a while.
また ここに来るっていう約束は
できないよ｡
So I can't promise that I'll be back.
これ あげる｡
You can have this.
ボリューム
これって…ＶＯＬ.２じゃん！
This is volume 2 of Olga learning to dance!
オリガのダンス成長記録の｡
いいの？
I can have this?
Yeah, I doubt it's that interesting, but...
見たって別に
面白くないと思うけど｡
たまに見てよね｡
I want you to watch me.
ゴメンな オリガ｡
I'm sorry, Olga.
土曜の約束｡
I won't be able to make it Saturday.
いいよ｡
あのブーツも とっとく｡
That's okay... I'll keep the boots in wraps.
どんどん履いてくれよ
靴は履くもんだ｡
You should wear them... That's what they're for.
あ～あ もう着いちゃった
ガガーリン像｡
We've already reached the Gagarin statue.
家まで送るよ｡
I'll walk you home.
い～んだってば
ここで｡
This is far enough.
それじゃ…オリガ｡
(オリガ)あっ そ～だ！
I guess this is it, Olga—
Oh, that's right!
ねぇ ヒビチョフ 知ってる？
Hey, Hibichov... Have you heard this?
この像は
２メートル以上あるけどさ➡
This statue is over two meters tall...
本当は この人
１５８センチだったんだよ｡➡
But he was actually only one hundred, and fifty-eight centimeters.
私より小柄｡
Shorter than I am.
But they lacked the technology to make Vostok 1 big enough for anyone taller.
だってね
当時のボストーク１号って➡
技術的に船室を広く作れなくて➡
大きい人は
乗れなかったんだって｡
だから
優秀な飛行士の中から➡
So Gagarin was chosen from a pool of qualified candidates due to his size.
小柄なガガーリンが
選ばれたんだって｡
詳しいっしょ 私｡
Aren't you impressed I know all this?
イヴァンに聞いたのか？
Did Ivan tell you that story?
うん １００回くらい…｡➡
Yep, a hundred times.
で その時のボストークって➡
And there was a 50-50 chance that, in space, they wouldn't be able to control Vostok.
実は帰還できるかどうか
五分五分だったんだよ｡➡
それを知らないガガーリンは
飛行中に自分が➡
When he received a double promotion mid-flight, Gagarin had no idea what was happening.
２階級も昇進したことを
告げられるの｡➡
うれ
本当なら 嬉しいところだけど｡
Normally, that would've been cause for celebration.
じゅんしょく
当時は殉職したパイロットを➡
But since awarding pilots posthumous double promotions was common at the time,
２階級昇進させてたから｡
ガガーリンは
自分もそうなるんだって➡
Gagarin could only wonder if he was about to die.
すごい不安になったらしいよ｡
詳しいっしょ 私｡
I know all the details.
他にも 色々 知ってるけど…
もう帰んないとね｡
I have more stories to tell you,
but I have to get home.
そ～だな 雪も降ってきたし｡
Yeah. Plus, it's snowing.
じゃね｡
Bye.
あとね！｢地球は青かった｣っての
有名でしょ？➡
One more thing.
You've heard of "The Earth is blue," right?
でも 本当はね ガガーリンは
もっと別の言い方したんだよ｡
But Gagarin actually phrased it differently.
へぇ～ 何つったの？
Oh? What did he say?
気になる？
Are you interested?
この続きは 次回 ヒビチョフが
またロシアに来た時に｡
When you come back to Russia, I'll tell you.
じゃね！イェーイ！
Bye! Yay!
ああ じゃあな オリガ！
Yeah! Goodbye, Olga!
ダンス 続けろよ～！
Keep dancing!
何で 最後に
ガガーリンの話なんか…｡
At the end, why was I telling stories about Gagarin?
⦅また ここに来るっていう約束は
できないよ⦆
So I can't promise that I'll be back.
ただいまより ヒューストン行きの
搭乗手続きを開始致します｡
We will now begin boarding for the flight to Houston.
《パニック障害を治したら➡
Once I've gotten rid of this panic disorder,
今度は 堂々と
またロシアに来る》
I can return to Russia on my own terms.
《まったく➡
Really... Why didn't I just say that?
何で そんくらいのことすらも
言えねぇんだ 俺は》
いいぞ オリガ！
Yes, yes! That's great, Olga!
You're on a roll today!
今日 調子いいな！
そこで 高く！ハイ！
Now, jump.
《また会いに来るよ…》
I'll come back to see you...
《オリガ…》
Olga.
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#80 Secret
How was Russia?
(六太)＜どうだったよ？ﾛｼｱは＞
＜寒かったよ＞
It was cold.
I wasn't asking about the weather...
＜気温 聞いてんじゃねぇよ｡
次のﾐｯｼｮﾝはどうなってんだ？＞
Do you know what your next mission will be?
Heading back to the moon?
＜次も月だろ？＞
＜ああ＞
Yeah.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Secret"
There's something you aren't telling me.
＜お前 何か隠してるだろう＞
Mr. Hibbit!
打ち上げ１５秒前…｡➡
T-15.
１４ １３ １２ １１…｡
14.
13.
12.
11.
ゼロ
このｶｳﾝﾄﾀﾞｳﾝが０を告げれば➡
Once the countdown reaches zero, we'll be off to space.
いよいよ 宇宙へ出発だ｡
ｶｳﾝﾄﾀﾞｳﾝの１の次は０じゃなく➡
The countdown ends with "ignition," not "zero."
イグニッション…意味は点火ね｡
That's when they ignite the boosters.
I'm n-n-not nervous about th-this at all!
おおお…お おいは
きききっ 緊張してないぜっぜ…｡
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝﾎｰｸ)ふ～ん｡
ニンジン食べる？
(ｶﾚﾝｷｬｯﾄ)いらニャい｡
Want some carrots?
No, thank mew.
緊張感のない連中ね～｡
They can't be serious, huh?
だいたい訓練の時から
ただ走りゃいいだけなのに➡
I mean, back in training, I told them to run, but they just stood around...
ボケッとしてるから…｡
早回し
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙﾋﾟｯｸﾞ)ワッハハハ…
行って来い おっ？
Off you go!
イグニッション…｡
Ignition!
ウオォーー！
あニャニャニャ…｡
あれ～ 声が…
震えて聞こえる…｡
My voice appears to be shaking...
Yay!
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝﾎｰｸ)あっ 浮いてる！
すごい 僕 浮いてるよ！
I'm floating!
Wow! I'm airborne!
Aren't you always airborne?
あ～んたは
いつも浮いてるじゃニャい｡
無重力 つまり重力が
ないということね｡
Zero gravity... In other words, there isn't any gravity here.
そうか～！
無重力ってことは➡
Oh, if there isn't any gravity, I can jump really high!
すっごい
ジャンプができるんだね！
あ こら
やめるんだ ヒビット｡
Wait... Don't do it, Hibbit.
無重力で 思いっきり
ジャンプなんかしたら➡
If you jump really high in zero gravity, you won't be able to stop yourself—
止まらなくなって…｡
イエーイ！
Yay!
イエッ イエッ イエッ…｡
Honestly... Hibbit never listens to anyone.
まったく ヒビットは
ちゃんと話を聞かん…｡
私は鼻が利くがね｡➡
I listen to my nose.
さて いよいよだ 諸君｡
Well, it's time, my friends.
月へ行こう！
Let's go to the moon.
Yay!
イエーイ！
あ だから飛ぶなって｡
(ｶﾚﾝｷｬｯﾄ)ニャアアー！もぉ～｡
I told you to stop jumping.
(ﾋﾋﾞｯﾄ)イエーイ イエーイ！
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨｺﾞﾘﾗ)うわっ あ あ 危ねぇ！➡
L-Look out!
Stay away!
こっち来んな！